[{"question": "In Which year, did the Indian National Congress(INC) for the first time demand a Constituent Assembly?\n\nA. 1934\n\nB. 1935\n\nC. 1936\n\nD. 1937\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. 1935"}, {"question": "The Idea of a constituent assembly for India was put forward first time in 1934 by:\n\nA. B G Tilak\n\nB. M K Gandhi\n\nC. M N Roy\n\nD. Motilal Nehru\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. M N Roy"}, {"question": "In which year, did the British Government accept the demand for framing of a constituent assembly for the first time?\n\nA. 1939\n\nB. 1940\n\nC. 1945\n\nD. 1946\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. 1940"}, {"question": "On which date Constituent Assembly was constituted under the scheme formulated by the Cabinet Mission Plan?\n\nA. November 1945\n\nB. December 1945\n\nC. November 1946\n\nD. December 1946\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. November 1946"}, {"question": "What was the total strength of the Constituent assembly in 1946?\n\nA. 292\n\nB. 296\n\nC. 389\n\nD. 412\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. 292"}, {"question": "Roughly one seat of Constituent assembly was allotted to how many populations?\n\nA. 1 Lakh\n\nB. 10 Lakh\n\nC. 50 Lakh\n\nD. 1 Crore\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. 10 Lakh"}, {"question": "Members of the Constituent Assembly were?\n\nA. All elected\n\nB. All Nominated\n\nC. Partly elected and Partly nominated \n\nD. None\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Partly elected and Partly nominated "}, {"question": "How many seats were won by Muslim League in the Constituent Assembly election?\n\nA. 15\n\nB. 73\n\nC. 93\n\nD. 208\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. 73"}, {"question": "Which of the following was not a member of the Constituent Assembly?\n\nA. Dr. Rajendra Prasad\n\nB. M K Gandhi\n\nC. H C Mukherjee\n\nD. Dr. Sachchidanad Sinha\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. M K Gandhi"}, {"question": "Which of the following was elected as the temporary president of the Constituent Assembly?\n\nA. Dr. Rajendra Prasad\n\nB. Jawahar Lal Nehru\n\nC. H C Mukherjee\n\nD. Dr. Sachchidanad Sinha\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Dr. Sachchidanad Sinha"}, {"question": "Which of the following was elected as the president of the Constituent Assembly?\n\nA. Dr. Rajendra Prasad\n\nB. Jawahar Lal Nehru\n\nC. H C Mukherjee\n\nD. Dr. Sachchidanad Sinha\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Dr. Rajendra Prasad"}, {"question": "Which of the following was elected as the president of the Constituent Assembly?\n\nA. Dr. Rajendra Prasad\n\nB. Jawahar Lal Nehru\n\nC. H C Mukherjee\n\nD. Dr. Sachchidanad Sinha\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Dr. Rajendra Prasad"}, {"question": "Which one of the following was/were elected as Vice-President of the Constituent Assembly?\n\nA. H C Mukherjee\n\nB. V T Krishnamachari\n\nC. Both\n\nD. None\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Both"}, {"question": "On which day did the Constituent Assembly hold its first meeting?\n\nA. November 9, 1946\n\nB. December 9, 1946\n\nC. November 9, 1947\n\nD. December 9, 1947\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. December 9, 1946"}, {"question": "How many members attended the first meeting of the Constituent Assembly?\n\nA. 296\n\nB. 211\n\nC. 208\n\nD. 312\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. 296"}, {"question": "On Which date historic ```Objectives Resolution``` was moved in assembly by Jawaharlal Nehru?\n\nA. November 9, 1946\n\nB. December 10, 1946\n\nC. November 12, 1946\n\nD. December 13, 1946\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. December 10, 1946"}, {"question": "On Which date historic ```Objectives Resolution``` was adopted by the Constituent assembly?\n\nA. December 13, 1946\n\nB. December 22, 1946\n\nC. January 12, 1947\n\nD. January 22, 1947\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. December 22, 1946"}, {"question": "The Mountbatten Plan is also called the partition plan, on which date Mountbatten Plan was accepted by both Muslim League and Congress.\n\nA. June 3, 1946\n\nB. June 13, 1946\n\nC. June 3, 1947\n\nD. June 30, 1947\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. June 3, 1947"}, {"question": "After the partition, what was the total strength(seats) of the Constituent Assembly?\n\nA. 399\n\nB. 299\n\nC. 296\n\nD. 229\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. 299"}, {"question": "Drafting Committee had how many members?\n\nA. 5\n\nB. 7\n\nC. 11\n\nD. 13\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. 11"}, {"question": "Total how many major committees were in the Constituent assembly?\n\nA. 5\n\nB. 7\n\nC. 8\n\nD. 9\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. 9"}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a major committee?\n\nA. Finance and Staff Committee\n\nB. Advisory Committee\n\nC. Steering Committee\n\nD. State Committee\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Advisory Committee"}, {"question": "Draft of Constitution was passed and adopted by Constituent Assembly on which date?\n\nA. November 24, 1949\n\nB. November 26, 1949\n\nC. January 24, 1950\n\nD. January 26, 1950\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. November 26, 1949"}, {"question": "Who is the father of the Indian Constitution?\n\nA. M N Roy\n\nB. Moti Lal Nehru\n\nC. Dr. B R Ambedkar\n\nD. Dr. Rajendra Prasad\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Dr. B R Ambedkar"}, {"question": "First Time ```Purna Swaraj``` day was celebrated on which date?\n\nA. November 26, 1929\n\nB. January 26, 1929\n\nC. November 26, 1930\n\nD. January 26, 1930\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. November 26, 1929"}, {"question": "Who gave the statement that  constituent assembly is ```a body of Hindus```\n\nA. Naziruddin Ahmed\n\nB. Granville Austin\n\nC. Lord Viscount Simon\n\nD. Winston Churchill\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Winston Churchill"}, {"question": "What was the symbol of the Constituent Assembly?\n\nA. Lotus\n\nB. Rising Sun\n\nC. Elephant\n\nD. Tiger\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Lotus"}, {"question": "Which of the following is described as the ```Soul of the Constitution```?\n\nA.  Fundamental Rights\n\nB.  Fundamental Duties\n\nC.  Directive Principles of State Policy\n\nD.  Preamble", "correct_answer": "D. Preamble"}, {"question": "The Preamble to the Indian Constitution is based on\n\nA.  Philosophy of India\n\nB.  ```Objectives Resolution``` drafted & moved by Pandit Nehru\n\nC.  Indian Culture\n\nD.  Religious Concept", "correct_answer": "B. ```Objectives Resolution``` drafted & moved by Pandit Nehru"}, {"question": "The term ```We``` in Preamble means\n\nA.  Indian Government\n\nB.  Supreme Courts\n\nC.  Indian Parliament\n\nD.  The People of India", "correct_answer": "D. The People of India"}, {"question": "Indian Constitution ensures ```Justice``` in which of the following form\n\nA.  Social\n\nB.  Economic\n\nC.  Political\n\nD.  All of the above", "correct_answer": "D. All of the above"}, {"question": "Preamble has been amended by which Amendment Act?\n\nA.  27th Constitutional Amendment\n\nB.  42nd Constitutional Amendment\n\nC.  44th Constitutional Amendment\n\nD.  40th Constitutional Amendment", "correct_answer": "C.  44th Constitutional Amendment"}, {"question": "In which case, the Supreme Court specifically opined that Preamble is ```not``` a part of the Constitution?\n\nA.  Berubari Union case\n\nB.  Kesavanada Bharati case\n\nC.  Both A.  & B. \n\nD.  None of the above", "correct_answer": "A.  Berubari Union case"}, {"question": "In which case, the Supreme Court rejected the earlier opinion and held that Preamble\n\nis an integral part of the Constitution?\n\nA.  Berubari Union case\n\nB.  Kesavanada Bharati case\n\nC.  Both A.  & B. \n\nD.  None of the above", "correct_answer": "B.  Kesavanada Bharati case"}, {"question": "The Preamble states that the Constitution derives its authority from\n\nA.  Indian Culture\n\nB.  Government of India\n\nC.  The People of India\n\nD.  Princely states", "correct_answer": "C.  The People of India"}, {"question": "42nd Constitutional Amendment (1976) added which of the terms to the Preamble\n\nA.  Socialist\n\nB.  Secular\n\nC.  Sovereign\n\nD.  Both A.  & B.", "correct_answer": "D.  Both A.  & B."}, {"question": "Which part of the Indian Constitution expressly declares that India is a Sovereign,Socialist,Secular Democratic Republic?\n\nA.  Fundamental Rights\n\nB.  Directive Principles of State Policy\n\nC.  Preamble\n\nD.  Fundamental Duties", "correct_answer": "C.  Preamble"}, {"question": "```Economic Justice``` as one of the objectives of the Indian Constitution has been provided in\n\nA.  the Preamble and the Fundamental Rights\n\nB.  the Preamble and the Directive Principles of State Policy\n\nC.  the Fundamental Rights and the Directive Principles of State Policy\n\nD.  None of the Above", "correct_answer": "B.  the Preamble and the Directive Principles of State Policy"}, {"question": "The correct sequence of the following words in the Preamble is\n\nA.  Sovereign, Democratic, Socialist, Secular, Republic\n\nB.  Sovereign, Socialist, Secular, Democratic, Republic\n\nC.  Sovereign, Socialist, Democratic, Secular, Republic\n\nD.  None of these", "correct_answer": "C.  Sovereign, Socialist, Democratic, Secular, Republic"}, {"question": "The Constitution of which country was the first to begin with a Preamble?\n\nA.  USA\n\nB.  India\n\nC.  Britain\n\nD.  Canada", "correct_answer": "A.  USA"}, {"question": "The ideal of Justice (Social, Economic and Political) in the Preamble draws its inspiration from\n\nA.  Russian Revolution\n\nB.  American Civil War\n\nC.  French Revolution\n\nD.  Japanese Constitution", "correct_answer": "C.  French Revolution"}, {"question": "The ideals of liberty, equality and fraternity in the Preamble have been taken from\n\nA.  French Revolution\n\nB.  Russian Revolution\n\nC.  American Civil War\n\nD.  None of the above", "correct_answer": "A. French Revolution"}, {"question": "Which of the following is true about Preamble?\n\nA.  It is a source of power to legislature and a source of prohibition upon the powers of legislature.\n\nB.  It is justiciable.\n\nC.  Its provisions are enforceable in courts of law.\n\nD.  None of the above.", "correct_answer": "A. It is a source of power to legislature and a source of prohibition upon the powers of legislature."}, {"question": "What does the term ```Secular``` mean in the Indian context?\n\nA.  All religions are equal in the eyes of the government and the State does not uphold any particular religion as its official religion.\n\nB.  Special importance to a religion related to minorities.\n\nC.  One religion is promoted by the government.\n\nD.  None of the following.", "correct_answer": "A. All religions are equal in the eyes of the government and the State does not uphold any particular religion as its official religion."}, {"question": "The 42nd Constitutional Amendment added which of the following words in the Preamble?\n\nA.  Socialist\n\nB.  Secular\n\nC.  Integrity\n\nD.  All of the above", "correct_answer": "D. All of the above"}, {"question": "Which of the following words is not mentioned in the Preamble to the Indian Constitution?\n\nA.  Sovereign\n\nB.  Socialist\n\nC.  Democratic\n\nD.  Indians", "correct_answer": "D. Indians"}, {"question": "The word ```Sovereign``` mentioned in the Preamble implies_____\n\nA.  India is an Independent State.\n\nB.  India is neither a dependency nor a dominion of any other nation.\n\nC.  India is free to conduct its own affairs (both internal and external).\n\nD.  All of the above.", "correct_answer": "D. All of the above."}, {"question": "Till now, the Preamble to the Constitution of India has been amended for how many times?\n\nA.  Once\n\nB.  Twice\n\nC.  Thrice\n\nD.  Never", "correct_answer": "C. Thrice"}, {"question": "In which of the following, are the basic aims and objectives of the Indian Constitution discussed?\n\nA.  Part -1\n\nB.  Preamble\n\nC.  Part \u00e2\u0080\u0093II\n\nD.  Schedule", "correct_answer": "B. Preamble"}, {"question": "Which among the following statements is incorrect?\n\nA.  The objective resolution passed by Pt. Nehru was what became the Preamble to the Constitution of India.\n\nB.  Preamble is enforceable in the court of law.\n\nC.  Preamble has been amended only once in 1976.\n\nD.  Preambles proves that the sovereignty lies ultimately with the Indian People.", "correct_answer": "C. Preamble has been amended only once in 1976."}, {"question": "42nd Constitutional Amendment was done in which year?\n\nA.  1976\n\nB.  1966\n\nC.  1986\n\nD.  1972", "correct_answer": "A. 1976"}, {"question": "Under which Article of the Constitution are the Cultural and Educational Rights granted?\n\nA. Article 29 and 31\n\nB. Article 29 and 32\n\nC. Article 29 and 30\n\nD. Article 30 and 31", "correct_answer": "A. Article 29 and 30"}, {"question": "Right to Constitutional Remedies comes under:\n\nA. Fundamental Rights\n\nB. Legal Rights\n\nC. Constitutional Rights\n\nD. Natural Rights", "correct_answer": "A. Fundamental Rights"}, {"question": "If an Indian citizen is denied a public office because of his religion, which of the following Fundamental Rights is denied to him? \n\nA. Right to Freedom\n\nB. Right to Equality\n\nC. Right to Freedom of Religion\n\nD. Right against Exploitation", "correct_answer": "B. Right to Equality"}, {"question": "Fundamental Freedoms under Article 19 are suspended during emergency caused by:\n\nA. war or external aggression\n\nB. failure of constitutional machinery of a State\n\nC. none of the given options\n\nD. financial crisis", "correct_answer": "A. war or external aggression"}, {"question": "Prohibition of discrimination on grounds of religion etc. (Article 15 of the Constitution  of India) is a Fundamental Right classifiable under: \n\nA. the Right to Freedom of Religion\n\nB. the Right against Exploitation\n\nC. the Cultural and Educational Rights\n\nD. the Right to Equality", "correct_answer": "D. the Right to Equality"}, {"question": "Any dispute regarding the violation of Fundamental Rights can be presented :\n\nA. in the Supreme Court only\n\nB. in the High Court only\n\nC. either in the Supreme Court or in the High Court\n\nD. first in the Supreme Court and then in the High Court", "correct_answer": "C. either in the Supreme Court or in the High Court"}, {"question": "Article 14 guarantees equality before law and equal protection of law to :\n\nA. all persons living within the territory of India\n\nB. all Indian citizens living in India\n\nC. all persons domiciled in India\n\nD. all persons natural as well as artificial", "correct_answer": "A. all persons living within the territory of India"}, {"question": "Untouchability is abolished and its practice is punishable according to :\n\nA. Article 15\n\nB. Article 16\n\nC. Article 17\n\nD. Article 15(4)\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Article 17"}, {"question": "Which of the following rights was described by Dr. B.R. Ambedkar as ```The Heart and Soul of the Constitution``` ?\n\nA. Right of Freedom of Religion\n\nB. Right to Property\n\nC. Right to Equality\n\nD. Right to Constitutional Remedies", "correct_answer": "D. Right to Constitutional Remedies"}, {"question": "Which of the following Fundamental Rights is also available to a foreigner on the soil of India?\n\nA. Equality of opportunity in the matter of public employment\n\nB. Freedoms of movement, residence and profession\n\nC. Protection from discrimination on grounds only of religion, race, caste or sex\n\nD. Protection of life and personal liberty against action without authority of law", "correct_answer": "A. Equality of opportunity in the matter of public employment"}, {"question": "According to Article 23, the following are prohibited:\n\nA. traffic in human beings, beggary, slavery and bonded labour\n\nB. monopoly of trade\n\nC. sale of incenses\n\nD. visit to terrorist infected areas", "correct_answer": "A. traffic in human beings, beggary, slavery and bonded labour"}, {"question": "Articles 20-22 relate to the fundamental right to life and personal liberty. These rights are available to :\n\nA. citizens and non-citizens\n\nB. natural persons as well as artificial persons\n\nC. citizen only\n\nD. all persons who have juristic personality", "correct_answer": "B. natural persons as well as artificial persons"}, {"question": "The total number of Fundamental Duties mentioned in the Constitution is :\n\nA. 9\n\nB. 10\n\nC. 11\n\nD. 12", "correct_answer": "B. 10"}, {"question": "Fundamental duties enacted in Part IV A of the Constitution are:\n\nA. enforceable duties and Parliament can impose penalties or punishments for the non- compliance\n\nB. like Directive Principles that : are mandates to people\n\nC. like Fundamental Rights that are enforceable\n\nD. no more than meant to create psychological consciousness among the citizens and of education value", "correct_answer": "D. no more than meant to create psychological consciousness among the citizens and of education value"}, {"question": "Fundamental duties have been added in the Constitution by 42nd Amendment Act, 1976 in accordance with the recommendations of:\n\nA. Santhanam Committee\n\nB. Sarkaria Committee\n\nC. Swaran Singh Committee\n\nD. Indira Gandhi Committee", "correct_answer": "A. Santhanam Committee"}, {"question": "Respect for the National Flag and National Anthem is:\n\nA. Fundamental Right of every citizen\n\nB. Fundamental Duty of every citizen\n\nC. Directive Principle of State policy\n\nD. ordinary duty of every citizen", "correct_answer": "B. Fundamental Duty of every citizen"}, {"question": "The Fundamental Duties:\n\nI. were introduced by the 44th Amendment.\n\nII. are incorporated in Part Ill-A.\n\nIII. are not justiciable.\n\nA. I and II\n\nB. I and III\n\nC. II and III\n\nD. III only", "correct_answer": "B. I and III"}, {"question": "Which of the following are envisaged as being part of the ```Right against Exploitation``` in the Constitution of India?\n\n1. Prohibition of traffic in human beings and forced labour.\n\n2. Abolition of untouchability.\n\n3. Protection of the interests of the minorities.\n\n4. Prohibition of employment of children in factories and mines. Select the correct answer using the code given below:\n\nA. 1 and 2\n\nB. 1 and 3\n\nC. 1 and 4\n\nD. 2, 3 and 4", "correct_answer": "A. 1 and 2"}, {"question": "Under the Constitution of India, which one of the following is not a fundamental duty? \n\nA. To vote in public elections\n\nB. To develop the scientific temper\n\nC. To safeguard public property\n\nD. To abide by the Constitution and respect its ideals", "correct_answer": "A. To vote in public elections"}, {"question": "The  Fundamental Right to________  has been deleted by the  __________Amendment Act.\n\nA. form associations; 44th\n\nB. property; 44th\n\nC. against exploitation; 42nd\n\nD. private property; 42nd", "correct_answer": "B. property; 44th"}, {"question": "Which Article of the Constitution of India says, ```No child below the age of fourteen years shall be employed to work in any factory or mine or engaged in any other hazardous employment```? \n\nA. Article 24\n\nB. Article 45\n\nC. Article 330\n\nD. Article 368", "correct_answer": "A. Article 24"}, {"question": "Which Article of the Constitution envisages free and compulsory education for children upto the age of 6 years? \n\nA. Article 45\n\nB. Article 19\n\nC. Article 29\n\nD. Article 32", "correct_answer": "A. Article 45"}, {"question": "Which part of the Constitution deals with the Directive Principles of State Policy?\n\nA. Part III\n\nB. Part IV\n\nC. Part V\n\nD. Part II", "correct_answer": "B. Part IV"}, {"question": "In the Constitution of India, promotion of international peace and security is mentioned in the: \n\nA. Preamble to the Constitution\n\nB. Directive Principles of State Policy\n\nC. Fundamental Duties\n\nD. Ninth Schedule", "correct_answer": "B. Directive Principles of State Policy"}, {"question": "The mind of the makers of the Constitution of India is reflected\n\nin which of the following?\n\nA. The Preamble\n\nB. The Fundamental Rights\n\nC. The Directive Principles of State Policy\n\nD. The Fundamental Duties", "correct_answer": "A. The Preamble"}, {"question": "Though the Directive Principles of State Policy contained in the\n\nConstitution are not enforceable by any court, yet they are:\n\nA. Fundamental in the governance of the country\n\nB. Binding on the State\n\nC. Enforceable at the instance of the President of India\n\nD. Superior to Fundamental Rights", "correct_answer": "A. Fundamental in the governance of the country"}, {"question": "Consider the following statements:\n\nDirective principles of State Policy are :\n\n1. Not amendable\n\n2. Not enforceable by any court\n\n3. Fundamental in the governance of the country\n\nWhich of the above statements are correct?\n\nA. 1 and 2\n\nB. 1 and 3\n\nC. 2 and 3\n\nD. 1, 2 and 3", "correct_answer": "B. 1 and 3"}, {"question": "In which of the following years the Fundamental Duties have\n\nbeen added in the Constitution of India? \n\nA. 1965\n\nB. 1976\n\nC. 1979\n\nD. 1982", "correct_answer": "D. 1982"}, {"question": "The Constitution of India adopted Fundamental Duties from the Constitution of \n\nA.America\n\nB.Japan\n\nC.Russia\n\nD.Britain", "correct_answer": "A. America"}, {"question": "When was the 11th Fundamental Duty added in the Constitution of India?\n\nA.1976\n\nB.1965\n\nC.1970\n\nD.None of the above", "correct_answer": "C. 1970"}, {"question": "Which of the pairs is correctly matched?\n\nA. Republic - Head of the State is hereditary Monarch\n\nB. Sovereign - Constitution rests on people```s will\n\nC. Democratic - Constitution does not recognise legal supremacy of another country\n\nD. Secular - State is without any religion of its own", "correct_answer": "B. Sovereign - Constitution rests on people```s will"}, {"question": "Which of the following items is wrongly matched?\n\nA December 9, 1947-Constituent Assemby```s first meeting\n\nB. November 26, 1949-the people of India adopted, enacted and gave to themselves the Constitution\n\nC. January 24, 1950-the Constitution was finally signed by the members of the Constituent Assembly\n\nD. January 26, 1950-the date of commencement of the Constitution", "correct_answer": "A December 9, 1947-Constituent Assemby```s first meeting"}, {"question": "In the Indian Constitution, Fundamental Duties are given in which article?\n\nA.Article 12 to 35\n\nB.Article 51A\n\nC.Article 36 to 50\n\nD.Article 19", "correct_answer": "B.Article 51A"}, {"question": "Which Constitutional Amendment Act was passed to provide compulsory education to children between 6 and 14 years?\n\nA.82nd\n\nB.83rd\n\nC.86th\n\nD.84th", "correct_answer": "C.86th"}, {"question": "Which of the following is given the power to enforce the Fundamental Rights by the Constitution?\n\nA.All Courts in India\n\nB.The Parliament\n\nC.The President\n\nD.The Supreme Court and High Courts", "correct_answer": "D.The Supreme Court and High Courts"}, {"question": "Fundamental Rights\n\nA.Cannot be suspended\n\nB.Can be suspended by order of Prime Minister\n\nC.May be suspended on the will of President\n\nD.May be suspended during Emergency", "correct_answer": "A.Cannot be suspended"}, {"question": "In the Indian Constitution of the ```Right to Freedom``` is granted by four Articles which are\n\nA.Article \u00e2\u0080\u0093 19 to Article \u00e2\u0080\u0093 22\n\nB.Article \u00e2\u0080\u0093 16 to Article \u00e2\u0080\u0093 19\n\nC.Article \u00e2\u0080\u0093 17 to Article \u00e2\u0080\u0093 20\n\nD.Article \u00e2\u0080\u0093 18 to Article \u00e2\u0080\u0093 21", "correct_answer": "B.Article \\xe2\\x80\\x93 16 to Article \\xe2\\x80\\x93 19"}, {"question": "Which one of the following Articles of the Indian Constitution belongs to a different category?\n\nA.Article 14\n\nB.Article 15\n\nC.Article 16\n\nD.Article 19", "correct_answer": "D.Article 19"}, {"question": "Prohibition of discrimination on the ground of religion etc. (Article 15 of the Constitution of India) is a Fundamental Right classifiable under\n\nA.The Right to Freedom of Religion\n\nB.The Right against Exploitation\n\nC.The Cultural and Educational Rights\n\nD.The Right to Equality", "correct_answer": "C.The Cultural and Educational Rights"}, {"question": "Which one of the following right of Indian Constitution guarantees all the fundamental rights to every resident of a country?\n\nA. Right against exploitation\n\nB. Right to freedom\n\nC. Right to equality\n\nD. Right to constitutional remedies", "correct_answer": "D. Right to constitutional remedies"}, {"question": "Who Discovered the site Harappa?\n\nA. Sir Jhon Marshall\n\nB. R. D. Banerjee\n\nC. Daya Ram Sahni\n\nD. Sir M. Wheeler\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Sir Jhon Marshall"}, {"question": "Which of the following Harappan sites had a dock?\n\nA. Harappa\n\nB. Mahenjodaro\n\nC. Lothal\n\nD. Alamgirpur\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Lothal"}, {"question": "Which Harappan Site is associated with Rice cultivation?\n\nA. Kalibangan\n\nB. Harappa\n\nC. Ropar\n\nD. Lothal\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Kalibangan"}, {"question": "The Indus Valley people had trade relation with which contemporary Civilization?\n\nA. Egypt\n\nB. Greece\n\nC. Celyon \n\nD. Mesopotamia\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Mesopotamia"}, {"question": "At which Harappan site, traces of a horse (Wild Ass) has been found?\n\nA. Kalibangan\n\nB. Lothal\n\nC. Surkotda\n\nD. Suktagendor\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Surkotda"}, {"question": "A statue of bearded man was found at which IVC Site?\n\nA. Harappa\n\nB. Mahenjodaro\n\nC. Lothal\n\nD. Kot diji\n\n\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Mahenjodaro"}, {"question": "A stair cut water reservoir has been found at which IVC Site?\n\nA. Surkotada\n\nB. Kalibangan\n\nC. Dholavira\n\nD. Harappa\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Dholavira"}, {"question": "The scripts of the lndus Valley Civilization was?\n\nA. Boustrophedon still not satisfactorily deciphered\n\nB. Brahmi\n\nC. Nagri\n\nD. Devnagari\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Boustrophedon still not satisfactorily deciphered"}, {"question": "From which site , The copper chariot of Harappan times was found?\n\nA. Harappa\n\nB. Rakhigarhi\n\nC. Daimabad\n\nD. Banawali\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Rakhigarhi"}, {"question": "Kalibangan was situated on the banks of which river?\n\nA. Ravi\n\nB. Ghaggar\n\nC. Sutlej\n\nD. Luni\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Ghaggar"}, {"question": "What were the residential houses of Indus people made of generally?\n\nA. Mud\n\nB. Stone\n\nC. Copper\n\nD. Burnt bricks\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Burnt bricks"}, {"question": "In which Harappan city, drainage system was absent?\n\nA. Banwali\n\nB. Rakhigarhi\n\nC. Surkotoda\n\nD. Rangpur\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Banwali"}, {"question": "Decorative bricks used in the flooring only at which IVC site?\n\nA. Kalibangan\n\nB. Harppa\n\nC. Mahenjo daro\n\nD. Lothal\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Mahenjo daro"}, {"question": "In Which site of IVC, two rows of six granaries found?\n\nA. Harappa\n\nB. Mahenjo daro\n\nC. Banwali\n\nD. Amri\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Mahenjo daro"}, {"question": "Which is the only Harappan city without Citadel?\n\nA. Chanhudaro\n\nB. Harappa\n\nC. Amri.\n\nD. Banwal\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Chanhudaro"}, {"question": "Which Indus site was destroyed by Fire?\n\nA. Lothal\n\nB. Kalibanga\n\nC. Kot diji\n\nD. Amri\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Kalibanga"}, {"question": "The ruins of Harappa were first noticed by whom?\n\nA. Charles Mason\n\nB. Sahni\n\nC. M Wheeler\n\nD. MS Vats\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. M Wheeler"}, {"question": "Which one of the following Indus cities had houses with doors on the main street?\n\nA. Lothal\n\nB. Surkotoda\n\nC. Chanhudaro\n\nD. Banawali\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Chanhudaro"}, {"question": "From Which IVC Site, Bones of Camel were discovered?\n\nA. Kalibangan\n\nB. Lothal\n\nC. Harappa\n\nD. Mohenjodaro\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Kalibangan"}, {"question": "Mohenjadaro means the ```Mound of dead```. Which other Harappan site```s name gives the same meaning?\n\nA. Harappa\n\nB. Kalibangan\n\nC. Amri\n\nD. Lothal\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Kalibangan"}, {"question": "Remains of which animal has not been discovered in the Indus Valley Civilization?\n\nA. Lion\n\nB. Tiger\n\nC. Cow \n\nD. Elephant\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Cow "}, {"question": "Mahenjodaro was a part of which state/ Province?\n\nA. Gujrat\n\nB. Punjab (Pakistan)\n\nC. Baluchistan\n\nD. Sindh\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Sindh"}, {"question": "Which is the biggest/largest Harappan site in India?\n\nA. Rakhigrahi\n\nB. Dholavira\n\nC. Kalibangan\n\nD. Lothal\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Dholavira"}, {"question": "Which was the Westernmost Site of IVC?\n\nA. Manda\n\nB. Sutkagendor\n\nC. Daimabad\n\nD. Alamgirpur\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Sutkagendor"}, {"question": "Which was the Easternmost Site of IVC?\n\nA. Manda\n\nB. Sutkagendor\n\nC. Daimabad\n\nD. Alamgirpur\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Manda"}, {"question": "Which is the Southernmost site of IVC?\n\nA. Manda\n\nB. Sutkagendor\n\nC. Daimabad\n\nD. Alamgirpur\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Alamgirpur"}, {"question": "Which is the Northern most site of IVC?\n\nA. Manda\n\nB. Sutkagendor\n\nC. Daimabad\n\nD. Alamgirpur\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Manda"}, {"question": "What does the term Mahajanpadas symbolises?\n\nA. Amalgamation of a large number of rural and urban settlements\n\nB. Separation of a large number of rural and urban settlements\n\nC. Single state with single ruler\n\nD. Large Villages\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Amalgamation of a large number of rural and urban settlements"}, {"question": "How many states were in Mahajanpadas?\n\nA. 15\n\nB. 16\n\nC. 17\n\nD. 18\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. 18"}, {"question": "Which of the following Buddhist text provides the names of 16 Mahajanpadas?\n\nA. Jatakas\n\nB. Bhagga of Sumsumgiri\n\nC. Anguttara Nikaya\n\nD. Malvikagnimitran\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Jatakas"}, {"question": "Which of the following Mahajanpada was not republican state?\n\nA. Magadha\n\nB. Vajji\n\nC. Kamboja\n\nD. Kuru\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Kamboja"}, {"question": "Which of the following Mahajanpadas emerged as the most powerful kingdom?\n\nA. Maghadha\n\nB. Vatsa\n\nC. Kosala\n\nD. Avanti\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Maghadha"}, {"question": "In which Mahajanapada Gautama Buddha was died?\n\nA. Vatsa\n\nB. Kosala\n\nC. Malla\n\nD. Anga\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Malla"}, {"question": "Who transferred his capital of Magadha from Rajgir to Patliputra?\n\nA. Chandragupta II\n\nB. Ashoka\n\nC. Udayin\n\nD. Ajatshatru\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Udayin"}, {"question": "Who transferred his capital of Magadha from Patliputra to Vaishali?\n\nA. Asoka\n\nB. Dhanananda\n\nC. Shishunaga\n\nD. Kalashoka\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Kalashoka"}, {"question": "When Alexander invaded India, who was the rulers of Magadha?\n\nA. Mauryas\n\nB. Nandas\n\nC. Shishunagas\n\nD. Haryankas\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Haryankas"}, {"question": "In ancient India, the earliest capital of Magadha kingdom was at?\n\nA. Pataliputra\n\nB. Varanasi\n\nC. Vaishali\n\nD. Rajgir\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Rajgir"}, {"question": "Mahajanapada situated on the bank of river Godawari was?\n\nA. Asmaka\n\nB. Avanti\n\nC. Kamboja\n\nD. Vatsa\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Asmaka"}, {"question": "Upanishad are books on which topic?\n\nA. Philosophy\n\nB. Law\n\nC. Yoga\n\nD. Religion\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Philosophy"}, {"question": "Which of the following Jain text provides the names of 16 Mahajanpadas?\n\nA. Jatakas\n\nB. Bhagwati Sutra\n\nC. Anguttara Nikaya\n\nD. Malvikagnimitran\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Bhagwati Sutra"}, {"question": "Bimbisara Conquered which Mahajanapada and annexed it with Magadha?\n\nA. Anga\n\nB. Kashi\n\nC. Kosala\n\nD. Vajji\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Anga"}, {"question": "In which Mahajanapada , Mahavira Jain passed away?\n\nA. Vatsa\n\nB. Kosala\n\nC. Malla\n\nD. Anga\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Anga"}, {"question": "How many number of traditional Upanishads are there?\n\nA. 108\n\nB. 110\n\nC. 112\n\nD. 118\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. 108"}, {"question": "Which one of the following contains the Gayatri Mantra?\n\nA. Rig Veda\n\nB. Yajur Veda\n\nC. Upanishad\n\nD. Sama Veda\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Rig Veda"}, {"question": "The Gayatri mantra contained in Rig Veda is dedicated to which deity?\n\nA. Agni\n\nB. Marut\n\nC. Shiva\n\nD. Savitri\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Savitri"}, {"question": "The Vedic deity Indra was the god of which phenomenon?\n\nA. Indra\n\nB. Eternity\n\nC. Rain and Thunder\n\nD. Fire\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Rain and Thunder"}, {"question": "Which God was not worshipped during the time of Rig Vedic period?\n\nA. Indra\n\nB. Agni\n\nC. Marut\n\nD. Shiva\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Shiva"}, {"question": "```The world is god and god are my soul``` is the philosophy contained in the which text?\n\nA. Vedas\n\nB. Puranas\n\nC. Brahmanas\n\nD. Upanishad\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Upanishad"}, {"question": "Who is The expounder of Yoga Philosophy?\n\nA. Patanjali\n\nB. Gautam\n\nC. Jamini\n\nD. Sankaracharya\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Patanjali"}, {"question": "The mediator between man and god, according to the Rig Veda was\n\nA. Indra\n\nB. Agni\n\nC. Marut\n\nD. Asvins\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Agni"}, {"question": "Who among the following popularized the theory of ```Artic Region``` as the original home of Aryans?\n\nA. Macdonell\n\nB. Max Muller\n\nC. B.G. Tilak\n\nD. Dayananda Saraswati\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. Max Muller"}, {"question": "Which is the oldest Veda?\n\nA. Sama Veda\n\nB. Yajur Veda\n\nC. Atharva Veda\n\nD. Rig Veda\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. Rig Veda"}, {"question": "Which of the following was the main characteristics of the later Vedic Age?\n\nA. Varna System\n\nB.  Tribal Polity\n\nC.  Caste System\n\nD.  Food gathering practice\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Caste System"}, {"question": "The 9th Mandala of Rig Veda is devoted wholly to?\n\nA. Urvashi and the heaven\n\nB.  Soma\n\nC.  Indra and his elephant\n\nD.  Gods related to plant and drug\n\n", "correct_answer": "B.  Soma"}, {"question": "How many hymns are there in Rigveda?\n\nA. 1024\n\nB. 1028\n\nC. 1038\n\nD. 1048\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. 1024"}, {"question": "How many number of Purans are there?\n\nA. 10\n\nB. 18\n\nC. 20\n\nD. 25\n\n", "correct_answer": "B. 18"}, {"question": "Which is the largest Puran?\n\nA. Skanda Puran\n\nB. Vishnu Puran\n\nC. Markendaya Puran\n\nD. Matsa Puran\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. Skanda Puran"}, {"question": "Dhurupada Raga is mentioned in which Veda?\n\nA. Atharva Veda\n\nB. Rig Veda\n\nC. Sama Veda\n\nD. Yajur Veda\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Sama Veda"}, {"question": "Which Veda is known as the origin of Indian music?\n\nA. Atharva Veda\n\nB. Rig Veda\n\nC. Sama Veda\n\nD. Yajur Veda\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Sama Veda"}, {"question": "How many hymns were attributed to Agni?\n\nA. 250\n\nB. 200\n\nC. 150\n\nD. 100\n\n", "correct_answer": "A. 250"}, {"question": "The famous battle of 10 kings was fought on the bank of which in Rig Vedic period?\n\nA. Askini\n\nB. Parushini\n\nC. Saraswati\n\nD. Vipasha\n\n\n\n", "correct_answer": "C. Saraswati"}, {"question": "What do you mean by the supply of goods?\n\nA. Stock available for sale\n\nB. Total stock in the warehouse\n\nC. The actual production of the goods\n\nD. Quantity of the goods offered for sale at a particular price per unit of time", "correct_answer": "D. Quantity of the goods offered for sale at a particular price per unit of time"}, {"question": "What do you mean by ```under conditions of a perfect competition in the product market```?\n\nA. MRP = VMP\n\nB. MRP > VMP\n\nC. VMP > MRP\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "A. MRP = VMP"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the relation that the law of demand defines?\n\nA. Income and price of a commodity\n\nB. Price and quantity of a commodity\n\nC. Income and quantity demanded\n\nD. Quantity demanded and quantity supplied", "correct_answer": "B. Price and quantity of a commodity"}, {"question": "What do you mean by a mixed economy?\n\nA. Modern and traditional industries\n\nB. Public and private sectors\n\nC. Foreign and domestic investments\n\nD. Commercial and subsistence farming", "correct_answer": "B. Public and private sectors"}, {"question": "What do you mean by the demand of a commodity?\n\nA. Desire for the commodity\n\nB. Need for the commodity\n\nC. Quantity demanded of that commodity\n\nD. Quantity that consumers are able and willing to buy at various prices during any particular period of time", "correct_answer": "D. Quantity that consumers are able and willing to buy at various prices during any particular period of time"}, {"question": "Starting from the time of independence, why did India follow a planned economy?\n\n1.India followed a five-year plan and required an outlook.\n\n2.Directive Principles of Indian Constitution  indicated the planned vision of India.\n\n3.There was no indication whatsoever from the five year plans regarding how much of each and every good and service is to be produced.\n\n\n\nChoose the correct statements from the given options\n\nA. Only 2\n\nB. 2 and 3\n\nC. 1 and 3\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "C. 1 and 3"}, {"question": "What do you mean by Gross National Product?\n\nA. The total value of goods and services produced in the country\n\nB. The total value of all the transactions in the country\n\nC. The depreciation in the total value of goods and services produced in the country\n\nD. The total value of goods and services produced in the country and the net factor income from abroad", "correct_answer": "D. The total value of goods and services produced in the country and the net factor income from abroad"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the reason for the decline in the child sex ratio in India? \n\nA. Low fertility rate.\n\nB. Female foeticide\n\nC. Incentives for a boy child from the government\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "B. Female foeticide"}, {"question": "What factors are taken into consideration while revising the poverty line periodically?\n\nA. By conducting a survey every five years\n\nB. Survey carried out by National Sample Survey Organisation\n\nC. Both A and B\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "C. Both A and B"}, {"question": "In India, which banks/institutions have the highest share in the disbursement of credit to agriculture and allied activities?\n\nA. Cooperative banks\n\nB. Regional Rural Banks\n\nC. Commercial banks\n\nD. Microfinance institutions", "correct_answer": "B. Regional Rural Banks"}, {"question": "Which of the following is/are linked with the financial sector of India and controlled by the Reserve Bank of India (RBI)?\n\nA. Commercial bank\n\nB. Money lenders\n\nC. Stock exchange operations\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "A. Commercial bank"}, {"question": "When price floor is set above equilibrium price it will result in?\n\nA. Shortage\n\nB. Surpluses\n\nC. Equilibrium\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "B. Surpluses"}, {"question": "What is Gross Domestic Product?\n\nA. The total value of goods and services manufactured in the country\n\nB. The total value of all the transactions in the country\n\nC. The reduction in the total value of goods and services produced in the country\n\nD. The monetary value of all finished goods and services made within a country during a specific period.", "correct_answer": "B. The total value of all the transactions in the country"}, {"question": "Why is the unemployment rate low in India statistically?\n\n\n\n1. Unemployment is calculated only from the age group of 15 years to 59 years.\n\n2. Unemployment survives only when an individual cannot find a job.\n\n3. People are not interested in working outside the domestic area.\n\nChoose the correct option.\n\nA. Only 3\n\nB. 2 and 3\n\nC. Only 2\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "C. Only 2"}, {"question": "What does the bowed-out shape of the production possibilities curve illustrate?\n\nA. Law of increasing opportunity cost\n\nB. The production is inefficient\n\nC. The production is unattainable\n\nD. The demand is relatively elastic", "correct_answer": "A. Law of increasing opportunity cost"}, {"question": "What is the main economic problem faced by the society?\n\nA. Unemployment\n\nB. Inequality\n\nC. Poverty\n\nD. Scarcity", "correct_answer": "D. Scarcity"}, {"question": "What does ```Capitalism``` refer to?\n\nA. The use of market\n\nB. Government ownership of capital\n\nC. Private ownership of capital goods\n\nD. Private ownership of homes and cars", "correct_answer": "C. Private ownership of capital goods"}, {"question": "The goal of a pure market economy is to meet the desire of ______ .\n\nA. Consumers\n\nB. Companies\n\nC. Workers\n\nD. The government", "correct_answer": "A. Consumers"}, {"question": "What does the law of demand mean?\n\nA. As the quantity demanded rises, the price rises.\n\nB. As the price rises, the quantity demanded rises.\n\nC. As the price rises, the quantity demanded falls.\n\nD. As the supply rises, the demand rises.", "correct_answer": "C. As the price rises, the quantity demanded falls."}, {"question": "Which of the following is an example of an agricultural price support program?\n\nA. A price ceiling\n\nB. A price floor\n\nC. Equilibrium pricing\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "A. A price ceiling\\n\\nB. A price floor\\n\\nC. Equilibrium pricing\\n\\nD. None of the above"}, {"question": "What is the term for determining how resources are used?\n\nA. Allocative efficiency\n\nB. Utility distribution\n\nC. Equity allocation\n\nD. Resource allocation", "correct_answer": "A. Allocative efficiency\\n\\nB. Utility distribution\\n\\nC. Equity allocation\\n\\nD. Resource allocation"}, {"question": "Which of the following represents the basic concept of economics?\n\nA. Utility exists and scarcity is a reliable measure of how useful something is to someone.\n\nB. Scarcity is always a function of a resource exceeding demand.\n\nC. Scarcity exists and utility is a reliable measure of how useful something is to someone.\n\nD. Utility is a measure of how much someone will pay for a particular good based on need.", "correct_answer": "C. Scarcity exists and utility is a reliable measure of how useful something is to someone.\\n\\nD. Utility is a measure of how much someone will pay for a particular good based on need."}, {"question": "Ethan oversees a large company that produces a significant amount of both goods and services as well as economic profit. Which system of allocation is relevant to Ethan```s situation?\n\nA. Wealth standard\n\nB. Needs standard\n\nC. Contributive standard\n\nD. Equality standard", "correct_answer": "A. Wealth standard\\n\\nB. Needs standard\\n\\nC. Contributive standard\\n\\nD. Equality standard"}, {"question": "Which one of the following economic systems is characterized by state ownership of land and capital, but individuals remaining in control of their labor?\n\nA. Socialism\n\nB. Capitalism\n\nC. Traditional\n\nD. Communism", "correct_answer": "A. Socialism\\n\\nB. Capitalism\\n\\nC. Traditional\\n\\nD. Communism"}, {"question": "Name the state that introduced the ```Sujal -Drink-from-Tap``` project to provide 24\u00c3\u00977 piped pure drinking water.\n\nA.  Gujarat\n\nB.  Rajasthan\n\nC.  West Bengal\n\nD.  Odisha", "correct_answer": "A.  Gujarat\\n\\nB.  Rajasthan\\n\\nC.  West Bengal\\n\\nD.  Odisha"}, {"question": "Which of the following is a method to measure the National Income?\n\nA. Expenditure method\n\nB. Income method\n\nC. Product method\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "D. All of the above"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the correct term for calculating National Income at the market prices?\n\nA. Money income\n\nB. Non-monetary income\n\nC. Real income\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "A. Money income\\n\\nB. Non-monetary income\\n\\nC. Real income\\n\\nD. None of the above"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the correct term for calculating National Income at constant prices?\n\nA. Current income\n\nB. Domestic income\n\nC. Real income\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "C. Real income\\n\\nD. None of the above"}, {"question": "Which of the following items are not included while measuring the Gross National Product?\n\nA. Illegal and leisure activities\n\nB. Purely financial transactions\n\nC. Transferring of used goods and non-market goods and services\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "A. Illegal and leisure activities\\n\\nB. Purely financial transactions\\n\\nC. Transferring of used goods and non-market goods and services\\n\\nD. All of the above"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the employment theory related to?\n\nA. Macroeconomics\n\nB. Static economics\n\nC. Microeconomics\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "A. Macroeconomics"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the actual definition of transfer payments?\n\nA. Transfer payments refer to the payments made as compensation to the employees within an organisation\n\nB. Transfer payments refer to the payments made to workers on transferring from one job to another\n\nC. Transfer payments refer to the payments made without any exchange of goods and services\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "C. Transfer payments refer to the payments made without any exchange of goods and services"}, {"question": "The difference between the National Income and the Net National Product at market price is known as _______.\n\nA. National debt transfer\n\nB. Current transfers from the rest of the world\n\nC. Net indirect taxes\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "B. Current transfers from the rest of the world"}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a part of the National Income?\n\nA. Undistributed profits\n\nB. Income from government expenditure\n\nC. The interest amount on the unproductive national debt\n\nD. The payments made by a household to a firm for purchasing goods and services", "correct_answer": "D. The payments made by a household to a firm for purchasing goods and services"}, {"question": "Which of the following is another term for the Net National Product at factor cost?\n\nA. Personal Income\n\nB. National Income\n\nC. Gross National Product\n\nD. Net Domestic Product", "correct_answer": "D. Net Domestic Product"}, {"question": "Which of the following is true for Disposable Income?\n\nA. Disposable Income is the difference between Private Income and Indirect Taxes\n\nB. Disposable Income is the difference between Personal Income and Indirect Taxes\n\nC. Disposable Income is the difference between Private Income and Direct Taxes\n\nD. Disposable Income is the difference between Personal Income and Direct Taxes", "correct_answer": "B. Disposable Income is the difference between Personal Income and Indirect Taxes"}, {"question": "Which of the following organisations calculate the Gross Domestic Product in India?\n\nA. Reserve Bank of India\n\nB. Indian Statistical Institute\n\nC. National Statistical Office\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "C. National Statistical Office"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the correct definition for the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) of a country?\n\nA. The Gross Domestic Product is the total monetary value of the economic transactions within a country in a given year\n\nB. The Gross Domestic Product is the total value of both monetary and non-monetary goods and services in a country within a given year\n\nC. The Gross Domestic Product is the total value of tradable goods produced in a country within a given year\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "A. The Gross Domestic Product is the total monetary value of the economic transactions within a country in a given year"}, {"question": "Which of the following is true for Inflation?\n\nA. The value of money increases during Inflation\n\nB. The value of money decreases during Inflation\n\nC. The value of money stays the same during Inflation\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "B. The value of money decreases during Inflation"}, {"question": "Which of the following is true for Net National Income?\n\nA. The Net National Income is the total of Gross National Product and Depreciation\n\nB. The Net National Income is the difference between Gross National Product and Depreciation\n\nC. The Net National Income is the difference between Gross Domestic Product and Depreciation\n\nD. The Net National Income is the difference between Net Domestic Product and Depreciation", "correct_answer": "B. The Net National Income is the difference between Gross National Product and Depreciation"}, {"question": "Which of the following is true for the National Income of a country?\n\nA. If the savings exceed the investment within a country, the National Income will rise\n\nB. If the savings exceed the investment within a country, the National Income will fall\n\nC. If the savings exceed the investment within a country, the National Income will fluctuate\n\nD. If the savings exceed the investment within a country, the National Income will remain constant", "correct_answer": "B. If the savings exceed the investment within a country, the National Income will fall"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the definition of a closed economy?\n\nA. A closed economy is a type of economy where the money supply is totally controlled by the government\n\nB. A closed economy is a type of economy where neither exports nor imports take place\n\nC. A closed economy is a type of economy where deficit financing takes place\n\nD. A closed economy is a type of economy where there are no exports to other countries", "correct_answer": "B. A closed economy is a type of economy where neither exports nor imports take place"}, {"question": "The primary sector within a country for the calculation of National Income includes __________.\n\nA. Small scale industries\n\nB. Retail trading\n\nC. Agriculture\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "C. Agriculture"}, {"question": "Which of the following is included in the National Income of a country?\n\nA. Rent\n\nB. Interest\n\nC. Wages\n\nD. Rent, Interest, Wages, Salary, Profits", "correct_answer": "D. Rent, Interest, Wages, Salary, Profits"}, {"question": "What is the consumption of Fixed Capital known as?\n\nA. Depreciation\n\nB. Capital Formation\n\nC. Investment\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "A. Depreciation"}, {"question": "Which of the following is not needed while considering the Gross National Product?\n\nA. The net investment made by foreigners within a given period\n\nB. The total of private investments made within a given period\n\nC. The total purchase of goods made by the government within a given period\n\nD. The total per capita income of the citizens of a country within a given period", "correct_answer": "D. The total per capita income of the citizens of a country within a given period"}, {"question": "_________ poor are the people who move in and out of poverty on a regular basis.\n\nA. Occasionally\n\nB. Chronic\n\nC. Churning\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "C. Churning"}, {"question": "Which of the following is a characteristic of people below the poverty line?\n\nA. Debt trap\n\nB. Gender inequality\n\nC. Poor health\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "D. All of the above"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the full form of MPCE?\n\nA. Minimum per capita expenditure\n\nB. Maximum per capita expenditure\n\nC. Monthly per capita expenditure\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "C. Monthly per capita expenditure"}, {"question": "Which of the following are examples of self-employment programs in India?\n\nA. Swarna Jayanti Shahri Rozgar Yojna\n\nB. Prime Minister```s Rozgar Yojna\n\nC. Both A and B are incorrect\n\nD. Both A and B are correct", "correct_answer": "D. Both A and B are correct"}, {"question": "Which of the following is a part of transient poor?\n\nA. Churning poor\n\nB. Occasionally poor\n\nC. Both a and b are correct\n\nD. Both a and b are incorrect", "correct_answer": "C. Both a and b are correct"}, {"question": "In which year was the National Food for Work Programme launched in India?\n\nA. 2005\n\nB. 2004\n\nC. 2002\n\nD. 2001", "correct_answer": "B. 2004"}, {"question": "Which of the following programs was initiated by the Government of India to improve the food and nutritional levels of the poor in the country?\n\nA. Midday meal scheme\n\nB. Integrated child development scheme\n\nC. Public distribution scheme\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "D. All of the above"}, {"question": "Which of the following methods do economists use to identify the poor?\n\nA. Ownership of assets and occupation\n\nB. Annual income\n\nC. Savings\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "A. Ownership of assets and occupation"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the main reason behind the poor people in India getting limited economic opportunities?\n\nA. Lack of skills and basic literacy\n\nB. Scarcity of resources\n\nC. Most of them live in rural areas\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "A. Lack of skills and basic literacy"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the main reason for the decline in the per capita availability of land for the purpose of cultivation?\n\nA. Rapid growth of population and lack of employment\n\nB. Pollution in land and water bodies because of excessive usage of agrochemicals\n\nC. Frequent droughts\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "A. Rapid growth of population and lack of employment"}, {"question": "When was the Task Force on Projections of Minimum Needs and Effective Consumption Demand was formed?\n\nA. 1969\n\nB. 1979\n\nC. 1989\n\nD. 1999", "correct_answer": "B. 1979"}, {"question": "Those who regularly move in and out of poverty are called\n\nA. Chronically poor\n\nB. Churning poor\n\nC. Occasionally poor\n\nD. Transient poor", "correct_answer": "B. Churning poor"}, {"question": "Which of the following is an action adopted under the provision of minimum basic amenities to the people?\n\nA. Prime Minister```s RozgarYojna\n\nB. Swarna Jayanti Shahari RozgarYojna\n\nC. Pradhan Mantri Gramodaya Yojna\n\nD. National Rural Livelihood Mission", "correct_answer": "C. Pradhan Mantri Gramodaya Yojna"}, {"question": "NFWP was launched in:\n\nA. November 2004\n\nB. December 2003\n\nC. November 2002\n\nD. December 2005", "correct_answer": "C. November 2002"}, {"question": "......... scheme started in 1993 to create self-employment opportunities for educated unemployed youth in rural areas and small towns.\n\nA. National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (NREGA)\n\nB. Prime Minister Rozgar Yozana (PMRY)\n\nC. Swarnajayanti Gram Swarozgar Yojana (SGSY)\n\nD. National Rural Livelihoods Mission (NRLM)", "correct_answer": "B. Prime Minister Rozgar Yozana (PMRY)"}, {"question": "Choose the correct statement among the given set of statements.\n\nA. Odisha has the highest poverty ratio in India.\n\nB. MGNREGA was extended to whole India in 2nd February, 2006\n\nC. Relative poverty refers to the total number of people living below poverty line\n\nD. Inability to secure the minimum consumption needs of life is called poverty.", "correct_answer": "D. Inability to secure the minimum consumption needs of life is called poverty."}, {"question": "The major reason for fixing higher calorie intake for rural people is/are\n\nA. they are lethargic and thus require higher calorie intake\n\nB. they do more physical work than urban worker and thus require higher calorie intake\n\nC. Both (A) and (B)\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "C. Both (A) and (B)"}, {"question": "The government uses ......... as a proxy for income of households to identify the poor.\n\nA. quarterly per capita expenditure\n\nB. monthly per capita expenditure\n\nC. yearly per capita expenditure\n\nD. bi-yearly per capita expenditure", "correct_answer": "A. quarterly per capita expenditure"}, {"question": "Poverty gap implies the gap between the rich and the poor. The given statement is\n\nA. True     \n\nB. False\n\nC. Partially true       \n\nD. Partially false", "correct_answer": "B. False"}, {"question": "The calorie intake requirement has been fixed at a higher level for urban areas than rural areas. The following statement is\n\nA. True \n\nB. False\n\nC. Partially true     \n\nD. Partially false", "correct_answer": "A. True"}, {"question": "Seasonal workers comes under the category of......... .\n\nA. chronic poor      \n\nB. churning poor\n\nC. transient poor\n\nD. non-poor", "correct_answer": "C. transient poor"}, {"question": "Which of the given statement correctly explains the concept of poverty?\n\nA. Unable to meet the consumption of luxurious goods\n\nB. Unable to meet the minimum consumption of basic goods such as food, clothing etc\n\nC. Unable to have meet conspicuous consumption\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "B. Unable to meet the minimum consumption of basic goods such as food, clothing etc"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the cause of poverty in India?\n\nA. Low capital formation\n\nB. Lack of infrastructure\n\nC. Pressure of population\n\nD. All of the above\n\n", "correct_answer": "D. All of the above"}, {"question": "Wage policy of India is based on ...... .\n\nA. standard of living\n\nB. productivity\n\nC. cost of living\n\nD. None of these", "correct_answer": "B. productivity"}, {"question": "India follows ......... committee recommendations for estimating poverty line in India.\n\nA. Chelliah Committee\n\nB. Lakdawala Committee\n\nC. Dutt Committee\n\nD. Narasimham Committee", "correct_answer": "B. Lakdawala Committee"}, {"question": "What is the name given to the ratio which measures the number of poor below poverty live?\n\nA. Population ratio\n\nB. Poverty ratio\n\nC. Head count ratio\n\nD. Real poverty count ratio", "correct_answer": "C. Head count ratio"}, {"question": "Which of the given statements clearly explain the concept of absolute poverty?\n\nA. poverty in terms of absolute number of people\n\nB. poverty in terms of basic minimum calorie requirement\n\nC. poverty in terms of prevailing level of inflation\n\nD. poverty in terms of prevailing level of unemployment", "correct_answer": "B. poverty in terms of basic minimum calorie requirement"}, {"question": "Which of the following is not an instrument for estimation of poverty?\n\nA. Sen Index\n\nB. Poverty Gap Index\n\nC. Squared Poverty Gap Index\n\nD. Kuznets Curve", "correct_answer": "D. Kuznets Curve"}, {"question": "Which of the following is an accurate definition of a self-employed person?\n\nA. A self-employed person receives a salary from their employer on a regular basis\n\nB. A self-employed person owns as well as operate a business\n\nC. A self-employed person is employed only for a few months in a year\n\nD. All of the above", "correct_answer": "B. A self-employed person owns as well as operate a business"}, {"question": "Which of the following measures can help to reduce unemployment in a country within a very short period of time?\n\nA. Increasing the investment in both public and private sector\n\nB. Reducing the growth rate of a country```s population\n\nC. Reducing the inequalities in terms of distribution of wealth and income\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "A. Increasing the investment in both public and private sector"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the actual definition of a workforce?\n\nA. The workforce is defined as the labour force that is employed by another individual or organisation\n\nB. The workforce is defined as the total population that is not employed by another individual or organisation\n\nC. The workforce is defined as the total population that is forced to work by another individual or organisation\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "A. The workforce is defined as the labour force that is employed by another individual or organisation"}, {"question": "Which of the following is a major form of livelihood for Indians as it accounts for greater than 50 per cent of the total workforce?\n\nA. Regular salaried employment\n\nB. Casual wage labour\n\nC. Self-employment\n\nD. None of the above", "correct_answer": "C. Self-employment"}, {"question": "Which of the following statements is not true for a worker?\n\nA. Any person who is self-employed is not a worker\n\nB. Any worker has the right to temporarily abstain from their work due to any illness\n\nC. Any person who is helping the main worker is also called a worker\n\nD. A worker also contributes to the gross domestic product (GDP) of a country", "correct_answer": "A. Any person who is self-employed is not a worker"}, {"question": "Which of the following statements is true about disguised unemployment?\n\nA. The majority of disguised unemployed in India are found in the agriculture sector\n\nB. The majority of disguised unemployed in India are found in the trade sector\n\nC. The majority of disguised unemployed in India are found in the transport sector\n\nD. The majority of disguised unemployed in India are found in the manufacturing sector", "correct_answer": "A. The majority of disguised unemployed in India are found in the agriculture sector"}, {"question": "Which of the following statements is true about the primary sector?\n\nA. Mining and quarrying is a primary sector activity\n\nB. Trade is a primary sector activity\n\nC. Transport is a primary sector activity\n\nD. Construction is a primary sector activity", "correct_answer": "A. Mining and quarrying is a primary sector activity"}, {"question": "Which state has the largest area in India? \n\nA.\tUttar Pradesh \n\nB.\tMadhya Pradesh \n\nC.\tMaharashtra \n\nD.\tRajasthan", "correct_answer": "D. Rajasthan"}, {"question": "The Coast line of India is- \n\nA.\t5500km \n\nB.\t6500km \n\nC.\t7500km \n\nD.\t8400km", "correct_answer": "D. 8400km"}, {"question": "Where is Lakshadweep Island located? \n\nA.\tIndian Ocean \n\nB.\tBay of Bengal \n\nC.\tArabian Sea \n\nD.\tNone of these", "correct_answer": "A. Indian Ocean"}, {"question": "How many islands are there in Lakshadweep? \n\nA.\t17 \n\nB.\t27 \n\nC.\t36 \n\nD.\t47", "correct_answer": "C. 36"}, {"question": "Which of the following Indian state does not have any coastal border? \n\nA.\tGujarat \n\nB.\tGoa \n\nC.\tRajasthan \n\nD.\tMaharashtra", "correct_answer": "C. Rajasthan"}, {"question": "Diu is an Island- \n\nA.\tBesides Daman \n\nB.\tBesides Goa \n\nC.\tBesides Gujarat \n\nD.\tBesides Maharashtra", "correct_answer": "C. Besides Gujarat"}, {"question": "Which Himalayan peak is also called as Sagarmatha- \n\nA.\tNanga Parvat \n\nB.\tDhaulagiri \n\nC.\tMt. Everest \n\nD.\tKanchenjunga", "correct_answer": "C. Mt. Everest"}, {"question": "Which is the eastern most peak of Himalaya? \n\nA.\tNamcha Barwa \n\nB.\tAnnapurna \n\nC.\tKanchenjunga \n\nD.\tMt. Everest", "correct_answer": "A. Namcha Barwa"}, {"question": "Godwin Austin is a \u00e2\u0080\u0093 \n\nA.\tPass \n\nB.\tPeak \n\nC.\tTelescope inventor \n\nD.\tGeologist", "correct_answer": "B. Peak"}, {"question": "What is another name of Greater Himalayas? \n\nA.\tHimadri \n\nB.\tSahyadri \n\nC.\tAssam Himalaya \n\nD.\tShivalik", "correct_answer": "A.\\tHimadri"}, {"question": "Nag Tibba and Mahabharat Mountain Ranges are included in- \n\nA.\tCross Himalayan \n\nB.\tGreater Himalayan \n\nC.\tLesser Himalayan \n\nD.\tDown Ward Himalayan", "correct_answer": "C.\\tLesser Himalayan"}, {"question": "The gap of a Mountain which provides natural path is known as? \n\nA.\tValley \n\nB.\tHighway \n\nC.\tPass \n\nD.\tHighland", "correct_answer": "C.\\tPass"}, {"question": "Himalayan mountain range is an Example of\u00e2\u0080\u0093 \n\nA.\tVolcanic Mountains \n\nB.\tResidual Mountains \n\nC.\tBlock Mountains \n\nD.\tFold Mountains", "correct_answer": "D.\\tFold Mountains"}, {"question": "Indian desert is known as- \n\nA.\tGobi \n\nB.\tSahara\n\nC.\tThar \n\nD.\tAtacama", "correct_answer": "C.\\tThar"}, {"question": "The outermost range of Himalayas is called. _______ \n\nA.\tKali \n\nB.\tShiwaliks \n\nC.\tDehradun \n\nD.\tKumaon", "correct_answer": "B.\\tShiwaliks"}, {"question": "Nandadevi peak is located in_______State \n\nA.\tHimachal Pradesh \n\nB.\tUttarakhand \n\nC.\tUttar Pradesh \n\nD.\tSikkim", "correct_answer": "B.\\tUttarakhand"}, {"question": "Which State has the longest coastline? \n\nA.\tAndhra Pradesh \n\nB.\tMaharashtra \n\nC.\tGujarat \n\nD.\tKarnataka", "correct_answer": "C.\\tGujarat"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the highest peak in undisputed Indian territory \n\nA.\tMount Everest \n\nB.\tKanchenjunga \n\nC.\tNanda Devi \n\nD.\tNanga parbat", "correct_answer": "C.\\tNanda Devi"}, {"question": "Saddle peaks the highest peak of Andaman and Nicobar Islands is located in \n\nA.\tGreat Nicobar \n\nB.\tMiddle Andaman \n\nC.\tLittle Andaman \n\nD.\tNorth Andaman", "correct_answer": "A.\\tGreat Nicobar"}, {"question": "The place Sabarimala is situated in which of the following States? \n\nA.\tAndhra Pradesh \n\nB.\tTamil Nadu \n\nC.\tKerala \n\nD.\tKarnataka", "correct_answer": "C. Kerala"}, {"question": "The part of the Himalayas lying between Satluj and Kali rivers is known as ____________. \n\nA.\tPunjab Himalaya \n\nB.\tNepal Himalayas \n\nC.\tKumaon Himalayas \n\nD.\tAssam Himalayas", "correct_answer": "C. Kumaon Himalayas"}, {"question": "The expansion of India is between \n\nA.\t37\u00c2\u00ba 17``` 53`````` North and 8\u00c2\u00ba 6``` 28`````` South \n\nB.\t37\u00c2\u00ba 17``` 53`````` North and 8\u00c2\u00ba 4``` 28`````` South \n\nC.\t37\u00c2\u00ba 17``` 53`````` North and 8\u00c2\u00ba 28`````` North \n\nD.\t37\u00c2\u00ba 6``` North and 8\u00c2\u00ba 4``` North", "correct_answer": "A. 37\u00b0 17` 53`````` North and 8\u00b0 4` 28`````` South"}, {"question": "The state of India through which Tropic of Cancer passes is \n\nA.\tJammu and Kashmir \n\nB.\tHimachal Pradesh \n\nC.\tBihar \n\nD.\tJharkhand", "correct_answer": "B. Himachal Pradesh"}, {"question": "Through how many Indian states does the Tropic of Cancer pass? \n\nA.\t6 \n\nB.\t8 \n\nC.\t7 \n\nD.\t9", "correct_answer": "C. 7"}, {"question": "Which important latitude divides India into almost two equal parts? \n\nA.\t20\u00c2\u00ba30``` South \n\nB.\t33\u00c2\u00ba 30``` North \n\nC.\t0\u00c2\u00ba \n\nD.\t23\u00c2\u00ba 30``` North", "correct_answer": "B. 33\u00b0 30` North"}, {"question": "The Southernmost point of India is \n\nA.\tKanyakumari \n\nB.\tRameshwaram \n\nC.\tIndira Point \n\nD.\tPoint Calimere", "correct_answer": "A. Kanyakumari"}, {"question": "Which one of the following pair of states of India indicates the Easternmost and Westernmost state? \n\nA.\tAssam and Rajasthan \n\nB.\tArunachal Pradesh and Rajasthan \n\nC.\tAssam and Gujarat \n\nD.\tArunachal Pradesh and Gujarat", "correct_answer": "B. Arunachal Pradesh and Rajasthan"}, {"question": "The Westernmost point of India is \n\nA.\t68\u00c2\u00ba 7``` W, Gujarat \n\nB.\t68\u00c2\u00ba 7``` W, Rajasthan \n\nC.\t68\u00c2\u00ba 7``` E, Gujarat \n\nD.\t68\u00c2\u00ba 7``` E, Rajasthan", "correct_answer": "A. 68\u00b0 7``` W, Gujarat"}, {"question": "Indian states bordering Bangladesh are \n\nA.\tWest Bengal, Nagaland, Assam, Meghalaya \n\nB.\tNagaland, Assam, Sikkim, West Bengal \n\nC.\tMeghalaya, Assam, West Bengal, Tripura \n\nD.\tNagaland, Assam, West Bengal, Tripura", "correct_answer": "C. Meghalaya, Assam, West Bengal, Tripura"}, {"question": "Which one of the following Indian states does not share border with Bhutan? \n\nA.\tSikkim \n\nB.\tMeghalaya \n\nC.\tArunachal Pradesh \n\nD.\tWest Bengal", "correct_answer": "B.Meghalaya"}, {"question": "Which one of the following States of India has international boundary on its three sides? \n\nA.\tAssam \n\nB.\tNagaland \n\nC.\tTripura \n\nD.\tWest Bengal", "correct_answer": "C.Tripura"}, {"question": "The group of Indian states neighbouring Nepal is \n\nA.\tSikkim - Bhutan \n\nB.\tSikkim - Bihar \n\nC.\tAssam - Bihar \n\nD.\tUttar Pradesh \u00e2\u0080\u0093 Haryana", "correct_answer": "B.Sikkim - Bihar"}, {"question": "What is Radcliffe line? \n\nA.\tAmerica - Canada boundary line \n\nB.\tIndo - Pakistan boundary line \n\nC.\tIndo - China boundary line\n\nD.\tRussia - Finland boundary line", "correct_answer": "B.Indo - Pakistan boundary line"}, {"question": "Pir Panjal Range is located/found in \n\nA.\tArunachal Pradesh \n\nB.\tJammu and Kashmir \n\nC.\tPunjab \n\nD.\tUttarakhand", "correct_answer": "B.Jammu and Kashmir"}, {"question": "Where is ```Mount Everest``` located? \n\nA.\tPakistan \n\nB.\tIndia \n\nC.\tTibet \n\nD.\tNepal", "correct_answer": "D.Nepal"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the highest mountain on Earth? \n\nA.\tMount Everest \n\nB.\tKanchenjunga \n\nC.\tLhotse \n\nD.\tMakalu", "correct_answer": "A.Mount Everest"}, {"question": "In India, how many States share the coastline? \n\nA.\t7 \n\nB.\t8 \n\nC.\t9 \n\nD.\t10", "correct_answer": "B.8"}, {"question": "Andaman and Nicobar are \n\nA.\tTwo Islands in Bay of Bengal \n\nB.\tGroup of Islands in Bay of Bengal \n\nC.\tGroup of Islands in Arabian Sea \n\nD.\tTwo Islands in Indian ocean", "correct_answer": "B.Group of Islands in Bay of Bengal"}, {"question": "Ten-degree channel separates \n\nA.\tAndaman from Nicobar Islands \n\nB.\tAndaman from Myanmar \n\nC.\tIndia from Sri Lanka \n\nD.\tLakshadweep from Maldives", "correct_answer": "C.India from Sri Lanka"}, {"question": "The Adam```s Bridge begins from \n\nA.\tDhanushkodi \n\nB.\tMandapam \n\nC.\tPamban \n\nD.\tRameshwaram", "correct_answer": "C.\\tPamban"}, {"question": "The three largest states of India in order of area are \n\nA.\tRajasthan, Madhya Pradesh, Maharashtra \n\nB.\tMadhya Pradesh, Rajasthan, Maharashtra \n\nC.\tMaharashtra, Rajasthan, Madhya Pradesh \n\nD.\tMadhya Pradesh, Maharashtra, Rajasthan", "correct_answer": "A.\\tRajasthan, Madhya Pradesh, Maharashtra"}, {"question": "Leh is the capital of \n\nA.\tDaman and Diu & Dadra and Nagar Haveli \n\nB.\tLadakh \n\nC.\tLakshadweep \n\nD.\tArunachal Pradesh", "correct_answer": "B.\\tLadakh"}, {"question": "Which of the following is not a Union Territory? \n\nA.\tGoa\n\nB.\tLakshadweep \n\nC.\tLadakh \n\nD.\tChandigarh", "correct_answer": "A.\\tGoa"}, {"question": "The territory of Puducherry lies divided in the States of \n\nA.\tTamil Nadu, Andhra Pradesh and Maharashtra \n\nB.\tTamil Nadu, Karnataka and Kerala \n\nC.\tTamil Nadu, Kerala and Andhra Pradesh \n\nD.\tTamil Nadu, Karnataka and Goa", "correct_answer": "B.\\tTamil Nadu, Karnataka and Kerala"}, {"question": "New Moore Island disappeared in the sea after many years of its creation. This island was claimed by which of the following two neighbours?\n\nA.\tIndia & Pakistan\n\nB.\tIndia & Sri Lanka\n\nC.\tIndia & Bangladesh\n\nD.\tIndia & Myanmar", "correct_answer": "C.\\tIndia & Bangladesh"}, {"question": "Which of the following was the former name of Indira Point?\n\nA.\tPygmalion Point\n\nB.\tCape Camorin\n\nC.\tCreek Point\n\nD.\tGuhar Moti", "correct_answer": "A.\\tPygmalion Point"}, {"question": "The longest beach of India is situated at which of the following place?\n\nA.\tMumbai\n\nB.\tChennai\n\nC.\tGoa\n\nD.\tTuticorin", "correct_answer": "B.\\tChennai"}, {"question": "Which one of the following caves is situated in Maharashtra? \n\nA.\tBadami \n\nB.\tAmaranth \n\nC.\tEllora \n\nD.\tBorra", "correct_answer": "C.\\tEllora"}, {"question": "The hill station of Chail is located in ______ \n\nA.\tHimachal Pradesh \n\nB.\tUttar Pradesh \n\nC.\tArunachal Pradesh \n\nD.\tMadhya Pradesh", "correct_answer": "A.\\tHimachal Pradesh"}, {"question": "India is a federal republic with 28 states and ________ union territories. \n\nA.\tSix \n\nB.\tFour \n\nC.\tFive \n\nD.\tEight", "correct_answer": "C.\\tFive"}, {"question": "Which of the following states separates Nepal from Bhutan? \n\nA.\tBihar \n\nB.\tSikkim \n\nC.\tOdisha \n\nD.\tAssam", "correct_answer": "B.\\tSikkim"}, {"question": "A chain of islands closely scattered in a body of water is called _________. \n\nA.\tCanyon \n\nB.\tArchipelago \n\nC.\tStrait \n\nD.\tReef", "correct_answer": "B.\\tArchipelago"}, {"question": "With how many states does Uttar Pradesh share its borders? \n\nA.\t7 \n\nB.\t8 \n\nC.\t9 \n\nD.\t6", "correct_answer": "D.\\t6"}, {"question": "The valley of Flowers National Park is located in _________. \n\nA.\tUttarakhand \n\nB.\tJammu and Kashmir \n\nC.\tHimachal Pradesh \n\nD.\tMeghalaya", "correct_answer": "A.\\tUttarakhand"}, {"question": "Which of the following latitudes passes through India? \n\nA.\tEquator \n\nB.\tArctic Circle \n\nC.\tTropic of Capricorn \n\nD.\tTropic of Cancer", "correct_answer": "D.\\tTropic of Cancer"}, {"question": "India is the seventh largest country in the world and it covers a total area of approximately: \n\nA.\t2700000 sq. km \n\nB.\t3000000 sq. km \n\nC.\t3200000 sq. km \n\nD.\t3600000 sq. km", "correct_answer": "C.\\t3200000 sq. km"}, {"question": "The largest southernmost single island in India is: \n\nA.\tRameswaram Island \n\nB.\tMinicoy Island \n\nC.\tCar Nicobar Island \n\nD.\tGreat Nicobar Island", "correct_answer": "D.\\tGreat Nicobar Island"}, {"question": "The Tropic of Cancer does not pass through: \n\nA.\tMadhya Pradesh \n\nB.\tWest Bengal \n\nC.\tRajasthan \n\nD.\tOrissa", "correct_answer": "B.\\tWest Bengal"}, {"question": "Which states of India have a common border with Pakistan? \n\n1. Jammu and Kashmir \n\n2. Himachal Pradesh \n\n3. Punjab \n\n4. Gujarat \n\n5. Rajasthan\n\n \n\nA.\tI, II, III, V \n\nB.\tI, II, III, IV \n\nC.\tI, III, IV \n\nD.\tI, III, IV, V", "correct_answer": "B.\\tI, II, III, IV"}, {"question": "Mac Mohan Line demarcates the boundary between: \n\nA.\tIndia and Pakistan \n\nB.\tIndia and China \n\nC.\tIndia and Nepal \n\nD.\tIndia and Bangladesh", "correct_answer": "B. India and China"}, {"question": "Kanchipuram is in which of the following states? \n\nA.\tKerala \n\nB.\tAndhra Pradesh \n\nC.\tTamil Nadu \n\nD.\tKarnataka", "correct_answer": "C. Tamil Nadu"}, {"question": "Nine Degree Channel separates: \n\nA.\tCar Nicobar and Great Nicobar \n\nB.\tLakshadweep and Minicoy \n\nC.\tLittle Andaman and Car Nicobar \n\nD.\tNorth Andaman and South Andaman", "correct_answer": "A. Car Nicobar and Great Nicobar"}, {"question": "India lies in the hemisphere: \n\nA.\tNorthern and eastern \n\nB.\tSouthern and eastern \n\nC.\tNorthern and western \n\nD.\tNorthern and southern", "correct_answer": "A. Northern and eastern"}, {"question": "West Bengal shares boundaries with how many foreign countries? \n\nA.\tOne \n\nB.\tTwo \n\nC.\tThree \n\nD.\tFour", "correct_answer": "B. Two"}, {"question": "The capital of Lakshadweep is: \n\nA.\tPort Blair \n\nB.\tSilvassa \n\nC.\tAizawl \n\nD.\tKavaratti", "correct_answer": "D. Kavaratti"}, {"question": "Which one of the following longitudes determines the Indian Standard Time? \n\nA.\t85.5\u00c2\u00baE \n\nB.\t86.5\u00c2\u00baE \n\nC.\t84.5\u00c2\u00baE \n\nD.\t82.5\u00c2\u00baE", "correct_answer": "C. 84.5\\xc2\\xbaE"}, {"question": "Between which one of the following pairs of islands is Duncan Passage located? \n\nA.\tSouth Andaman and Little Andaman \n\nB.\tLittle Andaman and Car Nicobar Island \n\nC.\tCar Nicobar Island and Little Nicobar Island \n\nD.\tLittle Nicobar Island and Great Nicobar Island", "correct_answer": "B. Little Andaman and Car Nicobar Island"}, {"question": "Port Blair - the capital of Andaman and Nicobar Islands, is located in which one of the following islands? \n\nA.\tNorth Andaman \n\nB.\tLittle Andaman \n\nC.\tMiddle Andaman \n\nD.\tSouth Andaman", "correct_answer": "D. South Andaman"}, {"question": "The ```Mahe region``` located on the western coast of India is politically a part of the Union Territory of: \n\nA.\tDadra and Nagar Haveli \n\nB.\tDiu and Daman \n\nC.\tLakshadweep \n\nD.\tPondicherry", "correct_answer": "D. Pondicherry"}, {"question": "The southernmost point of India is located in: \n\nA.\tKerala \n\nB.\tTamil Nadu \n\nC.\tLittle Andaman \n\nD.\tGreat Nicobar", "correct_answer": "B.Kerala"}, {"question": "At which place will you find maximum sunlight in December? \n\nA.\tPune \n\nB.\tLeh \n\nC.\tKolkata \n\nD.\tKanyakumari", "correct_answer": "D.Kanyakumari"}, {"question": "With how many states/Union Territories does Uttar Pradesh share its borders? \n\nA.\t7 \n\nB.\t8 \n\nC.\t9 \n\nD.\t6", "correct_answer": "C.9"}, {"question": "Which of the following at 23o30```N divided India into almost two halves? \n\nA.\tEquator \n\nB.\tTropic of Capricorn \n\nC.\tPrime Meridian \n\nD.\tTropic of Cancer", "correct_answer": "D.Tropic of Cancer"}, {"question": "Which of the following is the smallest neighbouring country of India in terms of population? \n\nA.\tAfghanistan \n\nB.\tMaldives \n\nC.\tBangladesh \n\nD.\tNepal", "correct_answer": "B.Maldives"}, {"question": "Which mountains are on India```s eastern border with Myanmar? \n\nA.\tSatpura \n\nB.\tVindhya \n\nC.\tKarakoram \n\nD.\tPurvanchal", "correct_answer": "D.Purvanchal"}, {"question": "Which of the following states separates Nepal from Bhutan? \n\nA.\tBihar \n\nB.\tSikkim \n\nC.\tOdisha \n\nD.\tAssam", "correct_answer": "B.Sikkim"}, {"question": "What is name of the capital of Nagaland?\n\nA.\tShillong\n\nB.\tAizawl\n\nC.\tKohima\n\nD.\tGangtok", "correct_answer": "C.Kohima"}, {"question": "Gir National Park is well known for Asiatic Lions. It is based in which state?\n\nA.\tGujarat\n\nB.\tUttarakhand\n\nC.\tSikkim\n\nD.\tKarnataka", "correct_answer": "A.Gujarat"}, {"question": "In January 2023, ```World```s First Palm-Leaf Manuscript Museum```\n\nwas inaugurated in which state of India?\n\nA. Telangana\n\nB. Kerala\n\nC. Tamil Nadu\n\nD. Andhra Pradesh", "correct_answer": "B.Kerala"}, {"question": "The Birsa Munda International Hockey Stadium, India```s largest\n\nhockey stadium, in terms of seated (chair) capacity of 20,000,\n\nhas recently (in Jan ```23) inaugurated in which state/UT?\n\nA. Delhi\n\nB. Jharkhand\n\nC. Odisha\n\nD. West Bengal", "correct_answer": "B. Jharkhand"}, {"question": "Indian Railways has recently (in Jan ```23) announced the plan to\n\nintroduce India```s 1st hydrogen-powered trains on its narrowgauge heritage lines to transform Indian locomotive mobility by\n\n___________.\n\nA. July 2023\n\nB. December 2023\n\nC. May 2023\n\nD. March 2023", "correct_answer": "A. July 2023"}, {"question": "In January 2023, ____________ became the first state in India to\n\ngo fully digital in its banking service.\n\nA. Gujarat\n\nB. Maharashtra\n\nC. Delhi\n\nD. Kerala", "correct_answer": "D. Kerala"}, {"question": "In Which state, the International Kite Festival 2023 was\n\ninaugurated in January 2023?\n\nA. Maharashtra\n\nB. Tamil Nadu\n\nC. Goa\n\nD. Gujarat", "correct_answer": "D. Gujarat"}, {"question": "In which city, PM Narendra Modi has recently (in Jan ```23)\n\nflagged off the ```MV Ganga Vilas```, the world```s longest river\n\ncruise?\n\nA. Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh\n\nB. Kolkata, West Bengal\n\nC. Rishikesh, Uttarakhand\n\nD. Lucknow, Uttar Pradesh", "correct_answer": "A. Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh"}, {"question": "Name the organisation that has recently (in Jan ```23) organized\n\nthe ```Sainya Ranakshetram 2.0```, a Cyber Threat Seminar and\n\nWorkshop.\n\nA. National Association of Software and Service Companies\n\nB. Data Security Council of India\n\nC. Indian Army\n\nD. All India Council for Technical Education", "correct_answer": "C. Indian Army"}, {"question": "___________ has recently (in Jan ```23) announced a target to\n\nbecome the ```first Green Energy State``` by the end of 2025.\n\nA. Gujarat\n\nB. Uttarakhand\n\nC. Uttar Pradesh\n\nD. Himachal Pradesh", "correct_answer": "B. Uttarakhand"}, {"question": "According to the Nikkei Asia report released in January 2023,\n\nIndia surpassed ________ as the world```s third-largest auto\n\nmarket in 2022.\n\nA. Russia\n\nB. Germany\n\nC. Japan\n\nD. Australia", "correct_answer": "C. Japan"}, {"question": "Which city will host India```s 1st ever ABB FIA Formula E World\n\nChampionship race in February 2023?\n\nA. Hyderabad, Telangana\n\nB. Chennai, Tamil Nadu\n\nC. Visakhapatnam, Andhra Pradesh\n\nD. Mumbai, Maharashtra", "correct_answer": "B. Chennai, Tamil Nadu"}, {"question": "Which company has recently (in Jan ```23) partnered with the\n\nBoard of Control for Cricket in India (BCCI) as the ```Official\n\nSponsor``` of the Indian Cricket Team?\n\nA. Kewal Kiran Clothing Limited\n\nB. Dream11\n\nC. Byju```s\n\nD. Tata Consultancy Services", "correct_answer": "C. Byju```s"}, {"question": "What are the Mascots of 5th edition of Khelo India Youth Games\n\n(KIYG) 2022 that was unveiled by the Chief Minister of Madhya\n\nPradesh, Shivraj Singh Chouhan in January 2023?\n\nA. Veera & Dhakad\n\nB. Asha & Mowgli\n\nC. Jaya & Vijay\n\nD. Ammu & Rongmon", "correct_answer": "A. Veera & Dhakad"}, {"question": "Gareth Bale has recently (in Jan ```23) announced his retirement\n\nfrom International Football. Which country did he represent in\n\nInternational Football?\n\nA. Germany\n\nB. Wales\n\nC. Poland\n\nD. Belgium", "correct_answer": "B. Wales"}, {"question": "Name the country that has recently (in Jan ```23) defeated\n\nBelgium to win the FIH Odisha Hockey Men```s World Cup 2023\n\nand claimed their 3rd hockey world cup title.\n\nA. Netherlands\n\nB. Germany\n\nC. Australia\n\nD. Spain", "correct_answer": "A. Netherlands"}, {"question": "Shyamal Ghosh, former Indian _________ player, passed away in\n\nJanuary 2023.\n\nA. Badminton\n\nB. Boxing\n\nC. Football\n\nD. Tennis", "correct_answer": "C. Football"}, {"question": "Name the Greece```s Last King & 1960 Olympic Gold Medalist who\n\nrecently (in Jan ```23) Passed Away.\n\nA. King Paul III\n\nB. Constantine I\n\nC. King Paul I\n\nD. Constantine II", "correct_answer": "C. King Paul I"}, {"question": "When was the 5th World Braille Day observed across the globe\n\nby the United Nations (UN)?\n\nA. 4th January 2023\n\nB. 3rd January 2023\n\nC. 2nd January 2023\n\nD. 1st January 2023", "correct_answer": "A. 4th January 2023"}, {"question": "When was the Pravasi Bharatiya Diwas (PBD), also known as\n\nthe ```Non-Resident Indian (NRI) Day``` celebrated across India?\n\nA. 9th January 2023\n\nB. 6th January 2023\n\nC. 8th January 2023\n\nD. 5th January 2023", "correct_answer": "B. 6th January 2023"}, {"question": "When was Parakram Diwas 2023 observed across India?\n\nA. 22nd January 2023\n\nB. 26th January 2023\n\nC. 23rd January 2023\n\nD. 21st January 2023", "correct_answer": "C. 23rd January 2023"}, {"question": "What is the tagline of Punjab National Bank (PNB)?\n\nA. Your Perfect Banking Partner\n\nB. Together We Can\n\nC. We Understand Your World\n\nD. The name you can bank upon", "correct_answer": "C. We Understand Your World"}, {"question": "Name India```s first Atmamirbhar human space flight, which will\n\nbe launched in 2024 by the Indian Space Research Organization\n\n(ISRO).\n\nA. Shukrayaan\n\nB. Aditya-L1\n\nC. Chandrayaan-3\n\nD. Gaganyaan", "correct_answer": "D. Gaganyaan"}, {"question": "In January 2023, India won the 1st ICC (International Cricket\n\nCouncil) Under-19 Women``` s T20 (Twenty 20) World Cup 2023 by\n\ndefeating which country?\n\nA. New Zealand\n\nB. Australia\n\nC. England\n\nD. West Indies", "correct_answer": "India"}, {"question": "Which city was recently (in Jan ```23) declared as the capital of\n\nAndhra Pradesh by the Chief Minister (CM) of Andhra Pradesh, YS\n\nJagan Mohan Reddy?\n\nA. Guntur\n\nB. Amaravati\n\nC. Visakhapatnam\n\nD. Tirupati", "correct_answer": "Amaravati"}, {"question": "Which company recently (in Feb ```23) announced a plan to launch an\n\nArtificial Intelligence (AI) powered chatbot called ```Bard```, to counter\n\nMicrosoft-backed ChatGPT tool?\n\nA. IBM\n\nB. Google\n\nC. Meta\n\nD. Twitter", "correct_answer": "Google"}, {"question": "Who is the current (as of Feb ```23) Comptroller and Auditor General\n\nof India?\n\nA. Shashi Kant Sharma\n\nB. Rajiv Mehrishi\n\nC. Girish Chandra Murmu\n\nD. Vinod Rai", "correct_answer": "Girish Chandra Murmu"}, {"question": "According to the Global Minority Report released by the Center\n\nfor Policy Analysis (CPA) in February 2023, which country topped\n\namong 110 nations for inclusivity measures towards\n\nreligious minorities?\n\nA. South Korea\n\nB. Japan\n\nC. India\n\nD. United States", "correct_answer": "India"}, {"question": "In which state/UT, the Geological Survey of India (GSI) has recently\n\n(in Feb ```23) discovered the Lithium Reserves for the 1st time?\n\nA. Karnataka\n\nB. Madhya Pradesh\n\nC. Jammu and Kashmir\n\nD. Jharkhand", "correct_answer": "Jammu and Kashmir"}, {"question": "According to the ```Electricity Market Report 2023``` released by the\n\nInternational Energy Agency (IEA) on 8th February 2023, Asia will\n\nuse half of the world```s electricity by ___________.\n\nA. 2025\n\nB. 2027\n\nC. 2024\n\nD. 2028", "correct_answer": "2025"}, {"question": "Name the company that has recently (in Feb ```23) introduced\n\n```Snapdragon Satellite```, the world```s 1st satellite-based two-way\n\ncapable messaging solution for premium smartphones.\n\nA. Micron Technology Inc\n\nB. Qualcomm Technologies Inc\n\nC. Microsoft Corporation\n\nD. Ericsson Limited", "correct_answer": "Qualcomm Technologies Inc"}]